<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript | console.blog( this.thought )]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-08T20:26:00-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter de Croos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Functional programming with ecmascript6 generators]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/02/08/functional-programming-with-ecmascript6-generators/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T19:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/02/08/functional-programming-with-ecmascript6-generators</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The web is abuzz right now with ecmascript 6 on the horizon. If you get not 0.11,
you can use them already server side. Once of the big features I'm excited about
are generators.</p>

<p>I've <a href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/01/22/javascript-generators-first-impressions/">blogged about them previously</a>
Alas, I've only found nothing out there on the web that covers anything beyond basic
instatiation and invocation. With just that to go on, it was hard for me to initially see
the hype. A few days ago, I had an appifany.</p>

<p>Generators are first class objects and like functions, they can be composed from smaller parts. Therefore,
much of we know about functions can be applied to generators!</p>

<p>On that note, I will lay the ground work for understanding how to really USE generators.</p>

<h3>It all starts with a bind</h3>

<p>If you've worked with javascript for any of length of time, You should be familiar with bind.</p>

<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
  var bind = function(fn, ctx, args) {</p>

<pre><code>args = Array.prototype.slice.apply(arguments, 2);
return function() {
  args2 = Array.prototype.slice.apply(arguments);
  return fn.apply(this, arguments);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>A function has 2 diffrent modes, literal and called.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Literal: a function itself, its not being run.
{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
var something = function() {
console.log('do something');
}
{% endcodeblock %}</p></li>
<li><p>Called: running the function which gives us its return value along with side effects.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
something();
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>The bind is implimented by taking a literal function and calling it within another
literal function passing along the context and possible arguments using .apply().</p>

<p>A Generator has 3 states,
  1. Literal: A literal Generator function
 {%codeblock lang:javascript %}
var Gen = function *() {
  var value = yield asyncTask();
  return value;
};
 {% endcodeblock %}
  2. Instantiated: a runnable instance is created by calling the Generator function
 {%codeblock lang:javascript %}
var gen = Gen();
 {% endcodeblock %}</p>

<ol>
<li>Run: You can then iterate through the generator by calling next()
{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
gen.next();
{% endcodeblock %}</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[koa: zero to todo list]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/02/01/koa-zero-to-todo-list/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-01T17:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/02/01/koa-zero-to-todo-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Note: you need to run node 0.11 with --harmony to run the code.</h2>

<p>From the creators of express comes a brand new framework for node powered by
the new ecmascript 6 generators syntax. <a href="http://koajs.com/">Koa</a> is an interesting
reimagining of how we will be able to build web applications in javascript.</p>

<h3>The old paradigm</h3>

<p>In the standard node library, The 'http' module is used to create servers.</p>

<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}</p>

<p>var server = http.createServer(function(req, res) {
  res.writeHead(200, {'Content-Type': 'text/plain'});
  //server logic goes here
  res.end('');
});</p>

<p>server.listen(3000, '127.0.0.1');
console.log('listening on port 3000');</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Express exposes a function that we can give to
http.createServer as a callback. Express middleware is a set of functions that
take 3 arguments, req, res and next. The middleware performs some operations, modifies
either the request or response objects and passed down to the next middleware in the stack
by calling next(). Its akin to a water flow model where the the response ends somewhere
near the end of the middleware stack.</p>

<h3>Enter Koa, The generators based framework</h3>

<p>Like express, Koa works internatlly by generating a callback that can be passed to
http.createServer().  Unlike Express, it uses generators to provide a much more fine grained
model of control flow.</p>

<p>A very basic koa app looks like this, lets make it serve up the contents of a file</p>

<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
var koa          = require('koa');
var Promise      = require('bluebird');</p>

<p>//creates promise yielding versions of fs
var fs = Promise.promisifyAll(require('fs'));
//create the koa instance
var app = koa();</p>

<p>app.use(function *(next) {
  //here's an example middleware that logs to the console
  console.log('timestamp: before request => ', time.now());
  yield next
  console.log('timestamp: after request  => ', time.now());
});</p>

<p>app.use(function *() {
  this.body = yield fs.readFileAsync('./app.js', 'utf8');
});</p>

<p>app.listen(3000);
console.log('now listening on port 3000');</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Unlike Express, the middleware is written using generators.
Downstream middleware in Koa flows upstream on return. Middleware
yields down stream by explicitly calling 'yield next.'. Upon return, the control
flow yields back up to where the upstream middleware yielded downstream.</p>

<p>Where Express passes native node req and res obects through to each function, Koa
manages a context where it encapsulates them behind an interface. They are still available
thrugh the 'this' keyword as this.req and this.res. However, Its not reccomended in
the docs that you work with these native objects. One could imagine calling this.res.end('')
would throw a monkey wrench in the control flow. Instead you are suppossed to work through
the this.response and this.request. Most of the methods are aliased directly to this. 'this.body'
for example, is aliased to this.response.body.</p>

<p>There does not yet appear to be a direct way to get
to the request body. The co-body parser accesses the req.body directly so while the docs say
don't do it, Koa is still young so you may have to get your hands dirty.</p>

<h3>A Todo app in koa</h3>

<p>Now that we've covered the basics, lets try something a little more complex. A todo
List seems like a good thing no one has ever tried to make before in any technology ever!
To simplify assumptions, lets just store the todos in memory.</p>

<p>By itself, Koa is very minimalistic. It does not provide body parsing, sessions, or
routing in the core. Unfortunatly Koa is still young so there just aren't that many
npm modules for it just yet. A quick search on <a href="https://github.com/koajs/koa/wiki">the Koa website</a>
shows that we do have the necessary modules for a basic todo.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://github.com/koajs/route">koa-route</a>: for routing</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/co-body">co-body</a>: for parsing the body of post requests</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/koajs/static">koa-static</a>: for serving up static assets</li>
</ol>


<p>Here's the basic server side api
{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
//jshint esnext
var koa          = require('koa');
var staticServer = require('koa-static');</p>

<p>//this allows us to parse the native req object to get the body
var parse        = require('co-body');</p>

<p>var router       = require('koa-route');
var _            = require('underscore');</p>

<p>var Promise      = require('bluebird');
var path         = require('path');</p>

<p>var fs = Promise.promisifyAll(require('fs'));
var app = koa();
//our very basic data store
var todos = [];</p>

<p>//gets us unique ids
var counter = (function() {
  var count = 0;
  return function() {</p>

<pre><code>count++;
return count;
</code></pre>

<p>  };
})();</p>

<p>//serve up the public directory where we have all the assets
app.use(staticServer(path.join(__dirname, 'public')));</p>

<p>app.use(router.post('/todos', function <em>() {
  /</em></p>

<pre><code>yield lets us pass asynchronous functions that return promises or thunks
It will freeze the middleware till its resolved and pass it back in.
</code></pre>

<p>  */
  var todo = (yield parse.json(this));</p>

<p>  todo.id = counter();
  todos.push(todo);
  this.body = JSON.stringify(todos);
}));</p>

<p>app.use(router.get('/todos', function *() {
  this.body = JSON.stringify(todos);
}));</p>

<p>app.use(router.delete('/todos/:id', function *(id) {
  todos = _(todos).reject(function(todo) {</p>

<pre><code>console.log('what? ', todo, id );
return todo.id === parseInt(id, 10);
</code></pre>

<p>  }, this);
  this.body = JSON.stringify(todos.sort(function(a, b) { return a - b;}));
}));</p>

<p>app.listen(3000);
console.log('listening on port 3000');
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cultofmetatron/koa-todo">Download the code on github</a>
The github version includes frontend code.</p>

<h4>A few things of note:</h4>

<p>The 'yield' keyword ca do some interesting things. If we pass into it
an asynchronous function that returns a thunk or promise, it will stop execution of
the middleware and wait till it resolves. It then returns the value of the promse or thunk
and resumes the generator. This is a hell of alot easier to read.</p>

<h4>A word of caution</h4>

<p>The 'yield' keyword lets us do some safe blocking but it isn't always the ideal solution.
While the event loop itself isn't blocked by it the way futures can, it does block resuming
of any operations that occur after it.</p>

<p>For example, if we run three asyncronous operations top to bottom that do not depend on
each other, like the following...</p>

<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
app.use(function *() {
  var a = yield async1();
  var b = yield async2();
  var c = yield async3();
});
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>This completely defeats the purpose of node's (almost automatic) concurrency. When we call
async1, we are blocking until async2 runs. This is unoptimal. It would be better to get the promises
for the three functions and yield on a merged promise.</p>

<p>{%codeblock lang:javascript %}
app.use(function *() {
  var a = async1();
  var b = async2();
  var c = async3();
  var result = yield Promise.all([a, b, c]);
});
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>I'm excited to cut my teeth on sme bigger problems. As the frameowrk matures, Its going to
allow more fine grained control for how we write the next generation of web applications.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lets build a backbone based framework!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/01/06/lets-build-a-backbone-based-framework/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T13:57:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2014/01/06/lets-build-a-backbone-based-framework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been building large scale applications in Backbone for about 8 months now.
In that time I've used throax as well as building custom solutions in backbone.</p>

<p>Last night, I live coded the creation of a demo backbone framework similar in features
to Thorax. I'm going to walk you through how
I've solved architectural problems in contructing a large scale backbone framework.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cultofmetatron/backbone-framework-example">Fork or watch it here</a></p>

<p>When building a large scale Backbone, there are several consderations to consider.</p>

<ul>
<li>How are we going to have templates load? Inline html declarations in the views do not scale</li>
<li>how do we handle render?</li>
<li>how do we handle child views?</li>
</ul>


<p>By default, backboneView.render() is a noop. Its meant to be overidden. Backbone.Events gives us
a nice set of methods to allow Backbone objects to listenTo() events off each other, However, the
actual bindings and callbacks are left to the implimenter.</p>

<h3>Loading Templates</h3>

<p>the first thing is figure out how we want the templates to load. If using a tool like require.js
or browserify, there are plugins for automatically compiling templates and sending to the client
just a compiled template function we can plug into out view. Since I'm trying to keep it simple,
the easiest way to get templates is to wrap your templates in a script tag. To prevent the browser
from executing it as javascript, we add a type that is not 'text/javascript'.</p>

<p>I like to use "text/template."</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:html %}
  <script type="text/template" data-name="templateName"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;!-- template contents goes here --&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </script>
{% endcodeblock%}</p>

<p>Transforming these into working templates is fairly straightforward. For each
script tag with type="text/template", run the template compiler over the html inside and
store it somewhere. In this case I add a data-name attribute which will be the key for the
hash I store the compiled template in.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cultofmetatron/backbone-framework-example/blob/master/public/javascripts/init.js">/public/javascripts/init.js</a>
{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  window.templates = {};
  var $sources = $('script[type="text/template"]');
  $sources.each(function(index, el) {</p>

<pre><code>var $el = $(el);
templates[$el.data('name')] = _.template($el.html());
</code></pre>

<p>  });
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>In this version, I chose to use express + jade, Of course writing underscore templates
in jade seemed a little odd so I delegated those to jade's include statement. I know there
are projects like jade-browserify so maybe I'll eventually update this using just jade.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cultofmetatron/backbone-framework-example/blob/master/views/layout.jade">/views/layout.jade</a></p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:jade %}
doctype html
html
  head</p>

<pre><code>title= title
link( rel="stylesheet", href='http://blog.peterdecroos.com/components/bootstrap/dist/css/bootstrap.css')
link( rel="stylesheet", href='http://blog.peterdecroos.com/stylesheets/style.css')
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/components/jquery/jquery.js")
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/components/bootstrap/dist/js/bootstrap.js")
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/components/underscore/underscore.js")
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/components/backbone/backbone.js")
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/javascripts/base.js")
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/javascripts/application.js")
</code></pre>

<p>  body</p>

<pre><code>block content
script(type="text/template", data-name="main")
  include templates/main.html
script(type="text/template", data-name="header")
  include templates/header.html
script(type="text/template", data-name="menuLinks")
  include templates/menulink.html
script( src="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/javascripts/init.js") 
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>The actual contents of the underscore templates in the *.html templates will
now be compiled and loaded into "templates[data-name]" where I can access it later.</p>

<h3>Creating our own Base Backbone Objects.</h3>

<p>The first thing we want to do is determie the shared behavior of backbone objects
in our app. For special cases we can overide them later. However, for the sake of time, we
want some decalrative way of telling the object what template to use and a default render()
method that we can use in most situations.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  //first we declare a namespace to store these new Objects
  application = {};
  application.BaseView = Backbone.View.extend({</p>

<pre><code>initialize: function() {
  Backbone.View.prototype.initialize.apply(this, arguments);
  if (this.model) {
    this.listenTo(this.model, 'change', this.render);
  }
  /*
    if the BaseView is extended with a tpl string, we want to 
    have that be available but we also want to be able to load 
    it at runtime and have it overide the base tpl string
  */
  this.tpl = options.tpl || this.tpl
  this.loadTemplate(this.tpl);
}
loadTemplate: function(tpl) {
  /*  
    if tpl is a function, we assign it directly, 
    otherwise, if its a string, we look it up
    in our templates map.
  */
  if (_.isFunction(tpl)) {
    this.template = tpl;
  } else if (_.isString(tpl)) {
    this.template = template[tpl];
  } else {
    throw new Error('tpl must be a function or a string!');
  }
}
render: function() {
  //see below
}
</code></pre>

<p>  });
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Next up we need to create a render function. Its arbitrary based on the particular
needs of your application. For most purposes however, Its sufficiant to make a
view's model's attributes available inside the templates.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  //from the render in the preceeding example
  render: function() {</p>

<pre><code>this.$el.html('');//empty the view's node
var context = {}; //create a context object
if (this.model) {
  _.extend(context, this.model.attributes);
}
this.$el.html(this.template(context));
return this;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Here's a great first start. Now any View that extends BaseView will have a
render. The only interface we must follow is that the View have a model
and a tpl which tells the View how to resolve this.template.</p>

<p>Of course there's a major component missing. Any good backbone framework
has a way of embedding subViews. Turns out its sort of tricky.</p>

<p>The Lifecycle of a Backbone view in this case is to listen to changes on
model and call render() which updates the view's $el property. Thus its
impossible to proceed until this.$el is completely demystified.</p>

<h4>what is $el?</h4>

<p>I've heard alot of confusion about the nature of 'this.$el'. Typically, a Backbone
View is a controller for a node. This node is a structure relevant to the
document object model.</p>

<p>you may be familiar with a dom object if you've used jquery.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  var $body = $('body'); // => returns a jquery wrapped object
  $body[0] //returns the wrapped object representing the body dom node.
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>In much the same way, a backbone view is a controller for a dom object.</p>

<p>You may have seen the kickstart for a backbone app that involves doing a jquery
lookup on a node and setting its html to your view's $el property</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  var $container =  $('.container');
  $container.html(view.render().$el);
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Assuming the render() method of the view returns 'this', then calling it before calling the
$el property guarantees that the dom object managed by the view will be updated before being
placed in the dom. When render() is called again, it updates the <em>contents</em> of that $el. The
$container has a reference to $el stored in it thus ensuring that calling render() will change
the webpage to reflect the latest state of the model.</p>

<h4>Extending out Render() to support subViews.</h4>

<p>With the afformentioned definition of $el in mind, The best way to embed a subview
(with string based template engines, you do something else with dom based ones.) is to do an
initial render of the dom node marking off somehow places to embed subviews. Then afterwards,
go back through the $el and systematically embed $el for each subview in their respective places.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  //updated render()
  this.$el.html('');
  var context = {};
  context._subView = function(viewName) {</p>

<pre><code>return '&lt;div class="subView view-' + viewName + '"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;';
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  if (this.model) {</p>

<pre><code>_.extend(context, this.model.attributes);
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  //pop it in the dom
  this.$el.html(this.template(context));
  //notice we do this AFTER we rerender the new this.$el
  var subViews = this.subViews;
  this.$el.find('.subView').each(_.bind(function(index, el) {</p>

<pre><code>var $el = $(el);
// view-
var subView = _(Array.prototype.slice.call(el.classList)).chain()
  .filter(function(className, index) {
    return (className.match(/^view-/));
  }, this)
  .map(function(className) {
    return className.slice(5);
  }, this)
  .value()[0]; //grab the first item
$el.html(subViews[subView].render().$el);
</code></pre>

<p>  }, this));</p>

<p>  return this;
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>There's a new things we've added to this version.</p>

<ol>
<li>There is now a 'subView()' helper being passed into context, this will generate
the slug that we will look for when embedding a subview.</li>
<li>After the $el is rendered, we are searching for dom elements with class subview</li>
<li>for each subView, we find the name of the subview we embed in there given as
view-[viewName] and look it up in the view's subViews key/val lookup object.
Its a property of teh parent view.</li>
</ol>


<p>With this, we now have an easy way of supporting subviews.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  childView = new application.BaseView({</p>

<pre><code>tpl: 'child'
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  var parentView = new application.BaseView({</p>

<pre><code>tpl: 'parent'
subViews: {
  child: childView
}
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  $('div.container').html(parentView.render().$el);</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>In parentView's template, its as simple as using out new subView helper</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:html %}
  <script type="text/template" date-name="parent"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;%= _subView('child') %&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </script></p>

<p>  <script type="text/template" date-name="child"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;span&gt; hi I'm the child view!! &lt;/span&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </script>
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>In the next installment in this series, we'll build a base ControllerView class which we
can use to render generic collections. Yes, they'll be embedable as subviews in our BaseView.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to lexically scope like a boss]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2013/07/16/lexically-scope-like-a-boss/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T22:27:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2013/07/16/lexically-scope-like-a-boss</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lexical scoping (scoping accordinng to location in source code) is probably one of
the most powerful features a programming language can have.
Today, I'm going to show you how to use lexical scoping to
create powerful abstractions. I will begin by introducing the concept of scope.
From there I will introduce a few rules for figuring out the scope of your variables
in javascript and then introduce the concept of a closure and how it will make you
positivly badass at Javascript.</p>

<h2>What is a scope?</h2>

<p>I'm assuming you have written code before. Hell, I'd dare assume you've written a <em>var.</em></p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
var variableName = "variable value";
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>What does it mean to use the <em>var</em> keyword? As you may know, good javascript has you
prepend all your variables with var. Most will also advocate wrapping all your code in
an immediatly invoked function.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
//this is being declared in the global scope.
//its functionally equivilant to window.foo or just plain foo
var foo = "super bar";</p>

<p>(function() {
  var foo = "inner bar";
  console.log('this foo refers to the foo inside this function ', foo);
})();
/<em> I don't always create inline annonymous functions, but when I do, I
immediatly invoke them. Live dynamically my friends &lt;3 </em>/</p>

<p>console.log('this one will print the top level: ', foo);</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Let's start with this relativly simple example to begin growing some understanding.
Internally, the interpreter/compiler represents scopes with a tree (in simple cases, just a linked list).
At each node in the tree is a dictionary of values that we refer to with the variable
names from your source code. When we refer to foo, the interpreter (or the compiler at compile time)
will look for it in the most immediate scope. If it doesn't find a value there, it will look
up the scope tree until it finds a node with a matching key/val and uses it for the current instruction.</p>

<p>Look at that previous code sample. If there wasn't a <em>var foo</em> at the top of the function,
The interpreter would look for scope[foo] and find that it isn't there. It would then look for an
entry named <em>foo</em> in the current scope's parent. That is the global scope where
the variable foo exists. It refers to the value "super bar."</p>

<h2>Creating scopes and determining the current scope's parent</h2>

<p>The rules for creating scopes differ between languages. In Javascript, we start new scopes with a
function.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
var foo = "global scope";
var goo = "ber";
(function() {
  var foo = "inner scope";
  (function() {</p>

<pre><code>var foo = "super inner scope bro!";
</code></pre>

<p>  })();
})();
{% endcodeblock%}</p>

<p>This creates a tree with three nodes we can visually represent
in pseudo-coffeescript.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:coffeescript %}
 scope_chain = global:</p>

<pre><code>              variables:
                foo: "global scope";
                goo: "ber"
              children:
                inner_scope:
                  variables:
                    foo: "inner scope"
                  children:
                    super_inner_scope:
                      variables:
                        foo : "super inner scope bro!"
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock%}</p>

<p>As you can see, we have three nodes and there are variables that are available
at each node. If you try to access a variable, the interpreter will look up the nodes
until it finds an entry that matches.</p>

<p>Lets go deeper. How about we not even bother with immediatly invoking the function.
How would that work?</p>

<p>The simple answer is that it changes nothing. The scope chain rules are consistent. The only difference
is that we now have two ways variables can enter the scope.</p>

<ol>
<li>Through the scope tree, variables in parent scopes are available.</li>
<li>When variables are injected in via the function arguments which can be
pulled from some other scope where we invoke the function.</li>
</ol>


<p>We delay the instantiation of the scopes until they are invoked later in the program.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  //scope A
  var binder = function(st) {</p>

<pre><code>//scope B
var state = st
return {
  set: function(newState) {
    //scope C
    state = newState;
    return state;
  },
  get: function() {
    //scope E
    return state;
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
{% endcodeblock%}</p>

<p>Scope order is created lexically. Each new function definition in the source (ie: text, hence the lexical)
is being read into the interpreter as a place to mark a new node in the scope chain on invocation.
I mentioned that the scope datastructure resembles a tree because both Scope C and E
belong to B as siblings. B in turn, belongs to A.</p>

<p>None of these functions are being invoked but the scope lookup rules are locked to A -> B, B-> C, B->E
Things get hairier when we invoke them.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  //scope A
  var b1 = binder(5);
  b1.get();   // => 5
  b1.set(2); // => 2
  b1.get(); // => 2</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock%}</p>

<p>How on earth is this function maintaining state? The Binder, on invocation, takes the argument 5
and creates a scope according to the rules set forward in the source code of binder.</p>

<p>Now, 2 is in Scope B and being assigned to the variable "state" we instantiated in scope B.
We then return the object back.</p>

<p>The object we get back from calling binder()  has two functions and thus two child
scopes of B, (C, and D) which  we return back to Scope A. via the return.</p>

<p>Now it gets weird. When we call b1.get(), we invoke a function from scope A
which internally has a scope C who's parent scope is scope B. It thus returns a value from scope B
back into scope A. Think of it like a closed loop of scopes. ie: a closure. ;)</p>

<p>This is pretty powerful. b1.set() does something similar only its injecting a variable from scope
A containing 2 into scope E where it is assigned to a variable in scope B and subsuquently returned.
B1.get(), on its next invocation returns the same value stored in that variable from the same scope
into scope A, the top level context.</p>

<p>We can use this to create objects with completely encapsulated states.
This gives us a leg up when trying to wrangle asynchrounous processes.</p>

<p>Here's an example of a function that runs a function passed as an argument after a delay.
while we wait for the function to fire,
we can register functions to be called when the function is resolved.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}</p>

<p>  //scope A
  var delay = function(fn, args, timeout) {</p>

<pre><code>//Scope B
var status = "pending"; //how we track what the status of the internal state is
var result; //where we are going to store the result of calling fn.
var deps = []; //where we store registered callbacks.

setTimeout(function() {
  //Scope C
  /* the scope chain from here is A -&gt; B-&gt; C
  this simply calls teh function and allows us to pass in the
  arguments as an array
  */
  result = fn.apply(this, args); //call the function
  status = "done";
  //we run through all the functions in deps and run them one
  //by one.
  deps.forEach(function(dep) {
    //Scope D
    dep.call(this, result);
  });
}, timeout);

//the two objects being returned have access to this scope
//which allows us to invoke them to affect this internal 
//environmental.
return {
  done: function(func) {
    //Scope E
    //A -&gt; B -&gt; C
    if (status === "pending") {
      deps.push(func);
    }
    if (status === "done") {
      func(result);
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  var promise = delay(function(msg) {</p>

<pre><code>//Scope F
return msg + " world";
</code></pre>

<p>  }, ["hello"], 3000);</p>

<p>  //by passing this function to done, you guarantee that
  //when the function passed into delay is called, it will pass
  //the result into the function passed in here.
  promise.done(function(result) {</p>

<pre><code>//Scope G
console.log(result);
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  //3000 milliseconds later
  //> "hello world"
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Yeah its a wee bit contrived but it illustrates a point. By using a closure to wrap a
bunch of data into this enclosed space, we can hide away some
pretty sophisticated machinery to invert the responsibilty of control. Now the
object maintains the state of the async call to the file and we register functions
that it will call when the async call is resolved. This removes alot of overhead for managing
async functions.</p>

<p>In Node.js, we pass a callback into the third paramater  for the standard library functions.</p>

<p>What if we could apply the same principle and get an object we could pass along functions to
and know it will take care of running them when the file is available?</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
var fileObject = function(fileName, encoding) {
  var fs = require('fs');
  var status = "pending";
  var result_data;
  var result_error;
  var deps_success = [];
  var deps_fail = [];
  var deps_always = [];
  var ret = {};
  encod = encoding || 'utf8';</p>

<p>  fs.readFile(fileName, encoding ,function(err, data) {</p>

<pre><code>result_data = data;
result_error = err;
if (!result_error) {
  deps_success.forEach(function(fn) {
    fn(result_data);
  });
  status = "success";
} else {
  deps_fail.forEach(function(fn) {
    fn(result_error);
  });
  status = "error";
}
deps_always.forEach(function(fn) {
  fn();
});
</code></pre>

<p>  });
  var queueFunction = function(list, fn) {</p>

<pre><code>list.push(fn);
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  var done = function(fn) {</p>

<pre><code>if (status === "done") {
  fn(result_data);
  return ret;
}
if (status === 'pending') {
  queueFunction(deps_success, fn);
  return ret;
}
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  var fail = function(fn) {</p>

<pre><code>if (status === "error") {
  fn(result_error);
}
if (status === "pending") {
  queueFunction(deps_fail, fn);
}
return ret;
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  var always = function(fn) {</p>

<pre><code>if (status === "pending") {
  queueFunction(deps_always, fn);
} else {
  fn();
}
return ret;
</code></pre>

<p>  };
  ret.done = done;
  ret.fail = fail;
  ret.always = always;</p>

<p>  //this exposes the status as a readonly property
  Object.defineProperty(ret, 'status', {</p>

<pre><code>get: function() {
  return status;
},
enumerable: true
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  return ret;
};</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Hey, that wasn't so bad. We return an object of three functions and
it will take care of running the appropriate functions based on the
status of the object's internal async operation when its resolved.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}</p>

<p>var newFile = fileObject('./hello.txt');</p>

<p>newFile.done(function(data) {
  console.log('two ' + data);
});</p>

<p>newFile.done(function(data) {
  console.log('one ' + data);
});</p>

<p>newFile.fail(function(err) {
  console.log('the file errored out. returned: ' + err);
});</p>

<p>newFile.always(function() {
  console.log('this always gets called');
});</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>In short, lexical scoping and closures are pretty damn awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Backbone, a short primer - Part 1: Models and Events]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2013/06/02/backbone-primer/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T14:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.peterdecroos.com/blog/2013/06/02/backbone-primer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been a few months since I've started using backbone on my personal projects.
Its a great library for rolling out MVC structure into your application but the
learning curve is pretty brutal.</p>

<p>The first step to really understanding the backbone.js framework.</p>

<h3>There is no framework</h3>

<p>Seriously, get it out of your head entirely that backbone is a frameowrk. Its far
too minimal. Backbone is more like a toolkit library for contructing MVC frameworks.</p>

<p>Backbone provides the following objects</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://backbonejs.org/#Model">Backbone.Model</a></li>
<li><a href="http://backbonejs.org/#Collection">Backbone.Collection</a></li>
<li><a href="http://backbonejs.org/#View">Backbone.View</a></li>
<li><a href="http://backbonejs.org/#Router">Backbone.Router</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The real key is how we use it. Like Chess, it can be
learned very quickly. the problem is that you also need to understand the tactics and strategies.
The offical docs leave a lot to the imagination and the examples are lackluster at best if they
exist at all.</p>

<h3>Backbone.Model</h3>

<p>Backbone.Model is a storage container where we can add and remove
items via <em>set</em> and <em>get</em> attributes.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}</p>

<p>  var newModel = new Backbone.Model();
  newModel.set('foo', bar);
  newModel.get('foo') // => 'bar'</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>You may be wondering why you don't use <em>newModel.foo = 'bar'?</em>
The real power in backbone is in the
events that models can fire. By having you access the model's attributes via
<em>set</em> and <em>get</em>, you ensure that the associated callbacks get fired everytime
an attribute is changed.</p>

<p>For example, in a View containing a Model,
when we change an attribute on the model via the setter and getter methods.
A callback automatically makes the model emit a 'change' event which we can set
the view to listen to and trigger a rerender.</p>

<h4>Extending Backbone.Model</h4>

<p>Backbone.Model is inherited using extend. This is also where we add methods
that may be specific to our particular subclass of Backbone.Model. For instance,
lets create a Comments model which may contain a username, content, rating
and timestamp.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
  var Comment = Backbone.Model.extend({</p>

<pre><code>//defaults are self explanatory
defaults: {
  rating: 0,
},
/*
 * initialize runs whenever new is called, it takes care of
 * setting up __super in the inheritance chain
 * there is also 'constructor' which overides the contructor entirely
 * leaving you to manually impliment the prototype chaining.
 * ie: only use constructor if you know what you are doing.
*/
initialize: function() {
  this.set('owner', getCurrentUser());
  this.set('timestamp', new Date());
},
upvote: function() {
  this.set('rating', this.get('rating')++);
  return this;
}
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  /<em> now we initialize the model passing in values in an object. </em>/</p>

<pre><code>var newComment = new Comment({
content: "backbone needs a library for reactive databindings",
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  newComment.upvote().get('rating'); // => 1</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>Here we've set up a basic backbone model for setting representing a comment.
In defaults, we put in an object of default attributes. You may be wondering why I
set up the owner and timestamp attributes in <em>initialize.</em></p>

<p>The defaults object and anything inside it is evaluated into a static object
inside the extend function call. Thus, if you were to try this</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
 var Comment = Backbone.Model.extend({</p>

<pre><code>//defaults are self explanatory
defaults: {
  rating    : 0,
  owner     : getCurrentUser();
  timestamp : (function() { return new Date() })();
}
...
</code></pre>

<p> })
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>you would find that every instance will have the same timestamp. To get around this,
I have the functionality for those defaults set to run in initialize.</p>

<h4>Backbone.Model events</h4>

<p>Backbone models should only broadcast events in order to notify things that
contain it. A model itself can contain another model as an attribute.</p>

<p>Backbone.Model's 'change' event fires when it detects a change in the value of the attribute.
If the value is a model, then a change in that model's attributes won't change the reference
to the model. Unlike the dom, we have to explicitly set up our own event bubbling.</p>

<p>To set up your own event delegation, you have to set up a listener in the parent model to listen for
events in the attribute model.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}</p>

<p>  var CommentHolder = Backbone.Model.extend({</p>

<pre><code>initialize: function() {
  /* We set up event listeners here
    the first argument is message being fired
    the second is the function to be invoked
    the third is the context for function to be called in
  */
  this.get('comment').on('all', this.bubble, this);
},
bubble: function() {
  // apply is used to propegate all possible arguments
  // that can be coming form multiple events.
  this.trigger.apply(this, arguments); //trigger is a backbone function
}
</code></pre>

<p>  })</p>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p><a href="http://backbonejs.org/#Events-catalog">'all'</a> is a backbone defined catch all event
that sends along the name of the event as the first argument. The model will listen
to its comment and broadcast any messages it recieves to any who would hear.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
